I was going to go over with you the whole
iba a repasar contigo también el el
Leticia Sofia thing too.
rollito el rollito Leticia Sofía que
Well, I think. Look, before I
Bueno yo creo Mira antes de que vuelva a
put the video back on, I think this is the
poner el vídeo creo que esta es la
most obvious proof of what really
prueba más evidente de lo que realmente
happens behind closed doors.
sucede de puertas para dentro total lo
What I don't know, of course, I think there are many
que no sé Claro yo creo que hay muchos
moments when you can't act, you
momentos no en los que no puedes actuar
can't follow protocol, you ca
no puedes estar siguiendo un protocolo
n't be there, you can't be
no puedes estar no puedes estar
aware of the press, no, because now
pendiente de la prensa no porque ahora
we're going to see this moment and we're going to see
vamos a ver este momento y vamos a ver
another
otro
more recent one in which it's clear that they've
más recient en los que ya se ve que han
learned to dissimulate when there's a camera.
aprendido a disimular cuando hay cámar
Okay, it's brutal, okay, let's see, so that
vale es brutal vale a ver para que la
people understand, here they are coming out of
gente entienda aquí están saliendo de
this. This is the Palma de
esto Esto es la capilla de palma de
Mallorca chapel. Okay, they are greeting the
mallorca vale van saludando la catedral
Palma cathedral during the Easter mass in
de palma en la misa de pascua del año
2018, years ago. This is okay. Well,
2018 hace c añitos de Esto vale Bueno
there we see the little girl, the
ahí vemos a la chiquilla que ahí la
little girl will be about 12 or 13 years old, the
chiquilla tendrá unos 12 o 13 años va la
royal family is greeting all the
familia real saludando a todos los
attendees. Okay, as they leave,
asistentes vale conforme van saliendo
the photographer who always
les acompaña El fotógrafo que siempre le
takes photos of the family accompanies them. The Queen
hace fotos a la familia y la Reina le
asks the photographer to take a photo of her, to
pide al fotógrafo que le haga una foto
take a photo of her with her.  two granddaughters
que le tome una foto con sus dos nietas
what happens at the moment that
qué es lo que pasa en el momento que la
Queen Letizia realizes that the queen
reina Leticia se da cuenta que la reina
emeritus is posing with the two girls
emérita está posando con las dos niñas
that she puts in front of her and that she doesn't want
que se pone delante y que no quiere que
that photo to be there Nan okay And here comes
haya esa foto que Nan vale Y aquí llega
the moment pum I mean this is tremendous
el momento pum o sea esto es tremendo
Look at the discomfort wait Let's see
Mira la incomodidad espérate Vamos a ver
because I think I have another video here
porque creo que tengo aquí otro vídeo
where Ah no well I don't have it I thought I
donde Ah no pues no lo tengo me creía
had another video where it was seen
que tenía otro vídeo donde se veía más
closer So we're going to have to see it
cerca Así que lo vamos a tener que ver
in this yes we're going to have to see it in
en este sí lo vamos a tener que ve en
this I mean look look at the minutes
este o sea fijaros fijaros los minutos
of discomfort in fact I think that here there
de de incomodidad de hecho creo que aquí
was Lucía a stumble of the king because the
hubo Lucía un tropiezo del rey porque el
king emeritus seemed to fall very
rey emérito como que se caía muy a
often no yes yes yes there I started to have
menudo no sí sí sí ahí ya empiez a tener
important mobility problems I think
problemas de movilidad importante creo
that something happened here he fell and it was much
que aquí pasó algo que se cayó y fue muy
talked about the fall from another plane
comentado la la caída desde otro plano
already from inside that it was and so and it was falling
ya de dentro que fue y así y se fue caer
also that he has fallen two or three times
también que se ha caído dos o tres veces
the king look here look at the hand of
el rey mira aquí fijaros en la mano de
the queen emeritus on
en la mano de de la reina emérita en el
Leonor's shoulder okay he's getting closer it goes it goes  is
Leonor vale se va acercando va va va
prohibiting the photo it's not going to go it's getting in the
prohibiendo la foto no va va poniéndose
way of the photo Queen Letizia
por medio de la foto la reina Leticia se
approaches she sees that she is posing and
acerca está viendo que está posando y se
approaches the girl touches her head and goes to
acerca la niña le toca la cabeza y le va
discreetly take the girl's grandmother's hand away from the girl
con disimulo a quitarle la mano a la
and the
niña y la
girl pulls the grandmother you know
niña le mete el tirón a la abuela sabes
the girl does like this f I mean it's key
la niña ha así f o sea es que es clave
eh the the pull like this of the girl's
eh el el el tirón así de la niña de la
grandmother's hand it's very clear boom and the
mano de la abuela es clarísimo pum y el
father giving a thousand dollars for a hole I mean
padre dando mil duro por un bujero o sea
Felipe is saying Oh my god you
Felipe está diciendo Ah madre mía me la
're confusing me here what Are you going to do to me
estáis liando aquí qué Me vas a hacer
here please behave okay look at the
aquí por favor comportar vale fíjate la
situation that even gets a little
situación que incluso un poco se hace un
confused with his legs go on eh Look V looks at him
lío con las piernas anda eh Mira V lo
clearly of course it's like What's going on What's
mira claro claro es como Qué pasa Qué
going on family all good How happy we are
pasa familia todo bien Qué contentos
eh hey you why do they do that man knowing that you knowing that you
eh oe tú por qué hacen eso tío sabiendo
are in front of
que estás sabiendo que estás delante de
everyone this image will haunt
todo el mundo esta imagen perseguirá a
Letizia forever Well then there's another
Leticia siempre Bueno luego hay otra
then there's this other take, me for example
luego hay esta otra toma yo por ejemplo
Lucia I don't know what you think but I don't
Lucía no sé qué piensas tú pero yo no le
see any importance in it because it could
veo importancia porque puede ser
easily be a
tranquilamente una mancha del
lipstick stain  okay basically another pose
pintalabios vale básicamente otra pose
Okay now they want to act like the
Vale ahora quieren hacer como si no ha
previous thing didn't happen he gives her a kiss on the
pasado lo anterior le da un beso en la
forehead
frente
and kisses the
y bes de la
fruit to put this it could
fru a poner esto puede ser
easily be that he has stained her
tranquilamente que que le haya manchado
lipstick but of course the queen doesn't
de labios pero claro que la reina no
wear lipstick But well
lleva los labios pintados Pero bueno
look boom kiss on the forehead and says can you
Mira pum beso en la frente y dice tú le
take the kiss away please be it's
quitas el beso por favor sea es
incredible it's incredible this who knows what
increíble es increíble esto a saber que
happened before Leonor Apo to her mother well
pasó antes Leonor Apo a su madre bueno
not the move I think the move here is
no la movida yo creo que la movida aquí
very clear she had a blunder there that is going to
clarísima I tuvo ahí una pifia que va a
be unforgivable and in fact this is the video
ser imperdonable y de hecho es el vídeo
that is going to haunt her forever whenever
que la va a perseguir siempre siempre
she wants to say It's not that my
que ella quiera decir No es que mi
relationship with my mother-in-law is wonderful You
relación con mi suegra es maravillosa Le
can show her this video of a moteca that
puedes poner este vídeo de moteca que
quickly dismantles the version that
rápidamente le desmonta la versión que
she can give and well
ella pueda dar y que bueno
later what she says all the
posteriormente lo que dice todos los
public events in which she has coincided
actos públicos en los que ha coincidido
with her eh fake laugh fake touching eh
con ella eh risa falsa toqueteo falso eh
always trying to show that they are
intentando siempre demostrar que son
lifelong friends and well behind closed
amiguis de toda la vida y y bueno de
doors who knows what
puertas para dentro a saber lo que se
grows but let's go that the relationship is not that it is
crece pero vamos que la relación no es
rotten it is that there is the
que esté podrida es que está lo
following Clear Look here here  look,
siguiente Claro Mira aquí aquí mira
trust yourself. This detail, this one is already
fíate tú Este detalle este este ya es
current, this one from a few months ago, okay. And
actual este de hace unos meses vale Y
look, it's not from a few months ago, it's not from the
mira no de hace unos meses no es es del
month of October, this is at the
mes de octubre esto es en la en los
Princess of Asturias Awards. Well, look,
premios princesa de asturia e Pues mira
and she approaches like it's a good vibe and they're
y se acerca como buen rollo y están
talking knowing that they're recording her,
hablando sabiendo que la están grabando
you know, I was going to tell you. Maybe she doesn't care,
sabes te iba a decir A lo mejor le da
or rather, she doesn't care what people
igual o sea le da igual lo que la gente
think, if she knows that they don't get along, that they
opine que si sabe que se llevan mal que
get along well. No, but well, if she plays
se llevan bien No pero bueno si hace
this role, I don't think she cares.
estos papel no creo que le da igual
Mainly because these gestures are more dem,
principalmente Porque estos gestos están
these gestures are super
dem más estos gestos son super
artificial and typical of someone who
artificiales y propios de alguien que lo
wants to achieve. Is that the camera,
que quiere conseguir Es que la cámara
besides, whenever she does it, the camera
además siempre que que lo hace la cámara
records her at the exact moment where it knows
la graba en el momento justo donde sabe
that they're
que que están
watching her. And why and what does she care if they
viéndola Y para qué y qué más le da si
don't get along, well, they don't get along,
no se llevan pues no se llevan
no, really, I, I think that deep down
no realmente yo yo creo que en el fondo
she knows that this kind of bad vibes
ella sabe que ese tipo de mal rollo
also harm the institution. And that
también perjudica la institución Y eso
's a reality. Go on, it will go more in that direction. Let's
es una realidad ir irá más por ahí vamos
listen to what
a escuchar lo que lo que opina sobre
Pilar Eire thinks about this. And then after posing
esto Pilar eire y luego después de posar
for the photographers, another moment took place,
por los fotógrafos tuvo lugar otro otro
for me, quite uncomfortable, which
momento para mí bastante incómodo que
was Doña Sofía.  to her granddaughter to Leonor to her
fue doña Sofía a su nieta a Leonor a su
oldest granddaughter and I think with a
nieta mayor y yo creo que con un gesto
loving gesture that all grandmothers do she
de cariño que hacen todas las abuelas
tried to brush her hair away from her face and
intentó apartarle el pelo de la cara y
then the granddaughter turned around and left without
entonces la nieta Se giró se fue sin
saying a word she went towards the
pronunciar palabras se fue hacia los
cars and then Leticia was going to
coches Y entonces Leticia la iba a
follow her and then Doña Sofía grabbed
seguir Y entonces doña Sofía le cogió
Leticia's arm tightly because
por el brazo a Leticia con fuerza porque
I put a close-up I opened it I
yo puse un primer plano lo abrí hice un
zoomed in the zoom that I'm doing now and
zoom el zoom que estoy haciendo ahora y
Doña Sofía's hand was planted on
la mano de Doña Sofía estaba clavada en
Leticia's arm She grabbed it and
el brazo de Leticia La agarró y y
Leticia didn't even turn around
Leticia no llegó ni siquiera a volverse
and I think she said something to her with a lot With a
y yo creo le dijo algo con mucho Con
lot of passion and I think she said something like this
mucha pasión y yo creo que le dijo algo
This is a supposition eh
así Esto sí que es una suposición eh
Because I still don't know how to read lips
Porque leer los labios todavía no sé
but I think she said something like this Let
pero yo creo que le dijo algo así Deja
one of the girls Come with me in
que una de las niñas Vengan conmigo en
the car because it's true that it looked a
el coche porque es cierto que quedaba un
bit lifeless that the other two
poco desangelado que los otros dos
were in two cars and yet Doña
fueran en dos coches y sin embargo Doña
Sofía Left alone then Leticia
Sofía Fuera sola entonces Leticia muy
smiling knowing that they were
sonriente sabiendo que la estaban
focusing on her waved like this with her arm she didn't
enfocando se desao así con el brazo no
do like this with her arm she waved and
hizo así con el brazo se desao y
continued walking she answered something and it was
continuó caminando contestó algo y fue
some
alguna de las nietas con ella o no y sí
of the granddaughters with her or not and yes no no it wasn't any of them So I think that at that moment something would happen someone would say something to her because you were forced to link arms at the waist and walk a few steps linked to I noticed it's Leticia of course
enlazadas a me fijé en es Leticia claro
and there all the journalists took advantage
y ahí aprovecharon todos los periodistas
to say the great harmony between Sofia
para decir la gran sintonía entre Sofía
and Leticia is what it's like not having
y Leticia es lo que tiene no tener la
Pilar's gaze laugh that we don't see the
mirada de Pilar reire que no vemos lo
same things that she sees of course
mismo que ve ella claro cámara
slow motion but pir alire let's see is very
lenta pero pir alire a ver es muy de
trustworthy to to see the to see everything
confianza para para ver el para ver todo
related to the royal house But on
lo relacionado con la casa real Pero en
some occasions a little bit of a
algunas ocasiones un poquillo
hater Yes yes a little bit no a little bit a little bit
hater Sí sí un poco no un poco a un poco
yes a little bit yes no a little bit but this This is
sí un poquillo sí no un poquito pero es
this is very expensive It's that I
que esto Es que esto es des carísimo Es
think it looks worse it's I'm telling you I'm telling you
que la yo creo que queda peor es te digo
one thing regarding the hater issue
te digo una cosa referente al tema hater
with the royal house I think that it's not that there are
con la casa real yo creo que no es que
haters of the royal house I It's that I think
haya hater de la casa real yo Es que
that lately eh they've had
creo que últimamente eh han tenido
so many blunders on one hand the issue of the
tantas pifias por un lado el tema del
emeritus and then Queen Leticia She will have
emérito y luego la reina Leticia Habrá
contributed Peace to the institution in certain
aportado Paz a la institución en ciertos
aspects but in another eh I think that
aspectos pero es que en otro eh creo que
what she has contributed has been an
lo que ha aportado ha sido una guerra
all out war Where there was Team Leticia Team
total Donde había Team Leticia Team
Sofia and that is where I think
Sofía y ahí es donde yo creo que reside
the main problem lies that she has not
el problema principal que ella pues no
known how to win
ha sabido meterse en el bolsillo a la
people over and the clearest example is that they
gente y la muestra más clara es que
did a survey eh I don't know if you
hicieron un una encuesta eh No sé si la
have it around there is a survey where
tendrás por ahí hay una encuesta donde
eh Queen Leticia gets the lowest
eh la reina Leticia obtiene la menor
score along with the emeritus king
puntuación junto con el rey emérito
while Doña Sofía acquires the
mientras que Doña Sofía adquiere la
second position just behind the
segunda posición justamente detrás de la
princess of honor it is a
princesa de honor se trata de una
very recent survey
encuesta muy reci
where the highest score I think is
la que la máxima puntuación creoo que es
an oo with a
un oo con
view but no this is not it is a survey
mira pero no este no es es una encuesta
between a survey where Leonor
entre una encuesta donde donde Leonor
has the highest score within
tiene la la máxima puntuación dentro de
the members of the royal house The
los integrantes de la casa real El rey
emeritus king is last with a fail
emérito está el último con un suspenso
with a 3 and a half Leonor has an 8
con un 3 y medio el Leonor tiene un 8
with something eh then follows Felipe VI with
con algo eh luego lo sigue Felipe vi con
a seven and a bit and then comes the Infanta
un siete y pico y luego va la infanta
Sofía and last along with the
Sofía y ya la última junto con el
emeritus is
emérito es
Leticia aunt but you are you are super
Leticia tía pero estás estás super
informed you know everything eh super clear
puesta te lo sabe todo eh s super claro
This is the vanity survey no  The
Esta es la encuesta de vanitati no
Vanitatis survey is one that came out just
encuesta vanitatis es una que salió
this week in the survey.
justo justo esta semana en la encuesta O
So it has to
sea que tiene que
be just this week. Yes, it's very
estar justo esta semana sí es muy
recent. The survey is super recent and
reciente la encuesta es super reciente y
the highest rated by far is
la mejor valorada con diferencia es la
Princess Leonor, which is where
princesa Leonor que de ahí viene lo de
the Leonor Mania comes from, the merchandising that they've
la Leonor Manía el merchandising que le
done for her and well, it attracts a
han hecho y bueno que atrae a un público
completely different audience than the one we're
completamente distinto al que estamos
used to seeing. And as a monarchist, she's a
habituados a ver e de monárquico es una
girl from the generation what's
chica de la generación lo que se le
called generation Z, a young woman who is super
llama generación Z una joven pues super
integrated and has studied an
integrada en ha estudiado un
international baccalaureate where she has
bachillerato internacional Donde ha
been with boys and girls from different
estado con chico y chicas de diferentes
cultures where she regularly wears sustainable fashion
culturas donde viste moda sostenible
made in Spain. And well, it
made in Spain habitualmente y y bueno al
seems that she is the highest rated because she has
parecer la mejor valorada porque ha
brought youth closer to the
hecho que la juventud se acerque a la
monarchy, something that hasn't happened for
monarquía algo que no sucedía desde hace
many years. And this is precisely what
muchísimos años y esto Precisamente es
I believe is saving her as an institution
lo que yo creo que como institución le
after all the
está salvando después de todos los
scandals of the emeritus king, which really,
escándalos del rey emérito que realmente
Princess Leonor has, I would say
pues la princesa Leonor tiene Yo diría
that a high percentage of youth are
que un un alto porcentaje de la juventud
in favor of her, except for the
a favor de ella quitando claro a los eh
republicans. But
republicanos Pero
well, but I can't find that survey, it can't
bueno pero no encuentro esa encuesta no
come up, yes, I'll look for it for a moment.  I
me sale sí te la Busco un momento no
meet You know there are many types of
encuentro Sabes que hay mucho tipo de
surveys about the
encuesta sobre la familia
royal family and you think that you think you know
real y tú crees que la tú crees tú sabes
that the I was going to tell you you think that the
que la la te iba a decir tú crees que la
queen is aware of these things
reina está pendiente de de estas cosas
of the surveys of who is her
de de las encuestas de quién es su
favorite Look, you know that once Auron
favorita de Mira sabes que una vez auron
Play said something about the king, I mean, King
Play dijo algo sobre el rey o sea el rey
Felipe, you know who Auron Play is yes a
Felipe sabes quién es auron Play sí un
youtuber no yes yes but no Auron didn't want to
youtuber no sí sí pero no no quiso auron
tell the one wait I'll see if I can
contar el que espérate voy a ver si lo
find it look I've already found it it's a a
encuentro mira yo ya lo he encontrado es
publication from the Spanish and it says
una una publicación de la español y dice
Princess Leonor is already the highest
la princesa Leonor ya es la figura mejor
rated figure in the royal family with a
valorada de la familia real con notable
high mark she scores an 8 with 2 the heir to the
alto puntúa un 8 con2 la heredera al
throne is well received by those
Trono cuenta con buena acogida entre los
under 30 and surpasses her father who
menores de 30 años y supera su padre que
has a 7 with TR Ah Look this
tiene un 7 con TR Ah Mira esto
is it Look really I think that the
es Mira realmente yo creo que la
assessment comes precisely because it has brought
valoración viene justamente porque ha
the monarchy closer to the
acercado a la monarquía a la población
younger population then Well I think that
más joven entonces Bueno creo que
indeed there is a Leonor Mania among
efectivamente hay una Leonor Manía de la
young people who are very in favor of the
gente joven que está pues muy a favor
type of good styling if they speak
del tipo de bueno el estilismo si habla
English if not well in general I'll tell you  Well, well, they
inglés si no bueno en general ya os digo
are relevant things, that is to say, the
que pues pues son cosas relevantes o sea
least are the King Emeritus and
los que menos es el el rey emérito y
Leticia, then, uh, second to last, Leticia,
Leticia después eh de penúltima Leticia
I think that she has not known how to manage
yo creo que no ha sabido gestionar
her role as queen first. I think that things
e su papel como reina Yo creo que se le
have gotten out of hand for her at no
ha ido de las manos ella en ningún
time. She reigns with luck. She is not going
momento ella reina con sorte ella no va
to inherit the throne in the way that
a heredar el trono de la manera en la
King Felipe did. I saw that
que lo ha hecho el rey Felipe vi que lo
her daughter will in the future. She
hará su hija en el futuro ella
simply has the
simplemente pues tiene la labor
super important institutional role
institucional superimportante al igual
as king, but she is not head of state. She is
que rey pero no es jefa de estado ella
not going to make decisions. She has
no va a tomar decisiones ella es tiene
a purely representative role for
un papel puramente eh representativo de
the institution.
la institución